[music]
So thanks for the introduction. Hi
everybody. So today I'm going to talk
about patterns we observe and uh about
the uh fascinating journey we had the
last three years with the upcoming
revolution. Um so we all went from uh
entering prompts to write some simple
scripts up to uh working with coding
agents and we are 100% convinced that we
are already in the intelligence
explosion scenario and that we not only
need uh to build agents by ourself but
that we need to build agents and
orchestrate agents that build and
orchest trait agents. I really could
talk a lot about this uh re occurring
pattern not only because it's a
interesting meta theme but it also could
fill up the entire talk without even
trying.
Um so this is roughly our journey. I
don't go too deep into it. I I'm pretty
sure everybody of you has had a similar
journey starting with co-pilot uh uh
using cursor a lot. Then as soon as the
coding agent and the CLI came out, we
switched over to them and pretty soon
and experienced that managing them in
parallel is a nice way to work with them
because I was a little bit tired waiting
for the finishing of one and I could
have the others working on different
tasks and that pretty much grew into a
pattern where I wanted to organize even
more of them and that's what we're going
to talk about today.
>> [clears throat]
>> uh when uh starting with the proposal
for the talk the landscape with the
coding agent was a little bit different.
So just to give another pattern from the
self similarity. So three years now the
last three months and what we observed
alone in the last three months and
changing the the daily behavior of
working with the coding agent was the
upcoming new models starting with GPT5
OPUS 4.1 uh uh and yeah GPT5 codec was a
little bit gamechanging. So before we
were a fans of cloud code and heavily
using cloud code on a daily base and
with with the GPT5 codeex we switched
and since like I don't know three or
four weeks codeex CLI is the main tool
we're working with. Uh besides this, so
we we are we are coming from a data
background and uh we run data pipelines,
we run crawlers and bots collecting data
from the web. And what we wanted to to
combine is the the idea how do the
coding agents work in the inner. And so
we we wipe coded an agent proxy to have
the uh agents uh coding agents run
through the proxy so that we can observe
the communication with the API. And yeah
this was one of the uh uh projects in
the last month. Uh the other is so if
you have one agent in a CLI in a shell
and another one and maybe at some place
at some point four or five or more uh
you want to have a tool to manage them
all and that's our agent squad. uh and
realizing that you are working on a
prompt engineering level, a context
engineering level, uh we wanted to check
how how are others doing this and so we
we uh um started coding uh and
extracting data from GitHub. That's some
aspect I'm going to show you.
Um this is one of the most general
patterns we see. So very important is
the meter uh uh chart which shows the
doubling of the length of coding task
right now every six to seven months and
what we think is that we are still not
converging but the the speed of the
acceleration is increasing. So still
acceleration of acceleration and this is
the one side and we we experience on
when working with the agents. So
sometimes we give them a to the task and
10 minutes later it's done and it's
perfectly done. Sometimes after 5 minute
failure, sometimes 30 minutes works
really good. And yeah, of course we need
a human in the loop to not only judge
the the results and go into the
specification, go into the review of the
results and the architecture, but to
orchestrate them at the moment. But what
we also observe is with the upcoming uh
tools and the MCP and the skills uh that
these agents are able to choose tools by
themselves, that they are able to
communicate uh with others by themselves
and that is a pattern we see that we can
um employ them in parallel and that the
agents are more and more able to to work
out stuff by themselves.
[clears throat]
as this is uh recorded for YouTube. Just
a quick poll. Uh the sample size of the
crowd, I would roughly estimate about
two to 300 people here. Um how many of
you are using coding agents in daily
life?
Yeah, that's 80 or [snorts] 90%. Who's
using code?
Half of it. Who's using codeex?
Oh, that's only like 5%. And who's using
other coding agents?
Half of it. Okay, cool. Interesting.
Nice. And who who of you is using agents
MD?
Half of the crowd. Perfect. Cool. So, uh
um then I don't need to dive too much
into it. So, agents MD is not only like
rules on how to set up a project and how
to achieve uh uh stuff and coding style
and standards, but it's also a place for
memory for the agent. So the agent can
put learnings into it, what to do and
what not to do. Um, and the question is
how is it organized and are there levels
of it? Because it's not only one file in
the root of the project, but you can
place agents MD on different levels and
you can organize the codebase, the
components, the agents you're building,
the tools and the knowledge. And this is
very similar to the uh uh skills
paradigm we talk in a minute. uh and you
can have um you so what we are doing is
we are not only using clo codeex but
also clo in parallel and the question is
how do you share rules between them and
it's one thing is you can add an add
agents MD in the clo MD so he knows
where to look at up or you just zoom
link to the same um rule file
[laughter and clears throat] and from
from the standards it's just traversing
the the history the file directory uh to
the parent directory and it's taking all
the rules it finds up up the directory.
So
what are the levels to influence the
behavior and the results of coding
agents? First and foremost the system
prompt. So there's this Andre Kapati
called it system prompt learning. So
through the change of the system prompt
we can change the behavior. we can
change which tool tools it uses and how
it's uses and so on. Uh then we have the
agents MD we talked about it's like a
rule like a skill set like like um a
memory and then of course we have the
most volatile area like the prompts. Uh
and the question is what to improve and
what to engineer to improve the results
and the behavior. And of course we can
change the system prompts but with every
new release nearly every day there might
be new tools and the system prompt we we
evolve that we changed doesn't work
anymore. So this is quite tough
situation. uh and the prompt of course
yeah we can engineer our prompt skills
but we need to somehow save and uh have
templates and use the templates though
there is in between um the place for a
rule for the skill set and for the
memory and the agents MD are quite a
good place and that's where what we
experience on the daily base if we uh
maintain this agents MD we are able to
give the coding agents the ability to
learn and to adapt the behavior to
projects and to situations. And yeah, we
we all know this uh uh skills pattern
and yeah, this is what we see with
agents MD, especially when we uh grow a
hierarchy of these rules and we give
every um component, every agent we have
in our stack or every uh uh script, we
give them an agent MD and then the
decoding agents know how to handle and
how to use it. And the question is how
do we build up the agents MD and then
then it comes to meta prompting because
these agents have are really smart and
whenever you encounter a problem while
running through some task you can tell
them oh please don't do this again and
adjust your rules to not do this again
in the future when you face the same
situation. So this is one and the other
is if you have finished like a session
and you developed a component with all
the tests and it's running and it's fine
then you can ask it please uh uh take a
lessons learned out of your sessions
make five reflect on your rule set make
five suggestions how to improve what to
expect and then you but wait for my
approval and then you can tell them yeah
rule out one sounds nice let let's
incorporate that round five, four is
nice. Let's do this. And that's how we
maintain and develop the rule set. And
that's how the agents learn
can learn. [clears throat]
So um talking about the skill pattern.
So this is a really really nice
abstraction from the entropic guys and
that's something we are used to do on a
daily base even before it was skill
called skills and it is asking the um
the coding agent to build a script or to
build a tool and uh coming from a data
data background and being data analysts
we wanted self similar and
self-reflecting tool and we ask it
please scan your home direct ctor
because there are the sessions are saved
and I'm not sure whether you you know
this but you can resume sessions and you
can fork sessions and uh the uh dialogue
all your prompts and the tool use and so
on reside in the home directory and we
ask uh uh codeex to build up a script to
collect and analyze these traces and to
collect tool usage and uh token usage
and the runtime. So not only you can
ingest and uh reflect did you do
something good or not too good but you
can collect data. So if you want on a
later point uh have some better decision
grounding for orchestrating more of them
then you need some abstraction
datadriven approach and this is how we
build a skill. The skill is called
analytical [snorts] tools.
>> [clears throat]
>> So um what we heard a lot today is these
projects drift and the number one
approach is testing testing testing and
these agents are really capable of
inventing tests and what we also
encountered is if you have the agent
using the tools CLI interactive shells
like you do it's even better to to fix
errors you encounter and have them find
these errors and what you also is these
models want to to fulfill the task and
they do and try very hard they work
around and they fake tests and that's
something we don't want so we tell them
a lot of time and that's rule number one
in agmd for testing no fa fake no mock
no stop you are a coding agent you are
able to code please code real code no
fakes
um next thing really important with
coding agents or with LLM in general is
context engineering so we we've seen in
the beginning the First of a message to
the LLM is a system prompt. Then the
rules and then then some user messages
with answers. Yeah. And this is called
context. And depending on how the
context and the chain of thought went uh
you might get good answers or not to get
good answers. And everybody noticed is
when the context fills or when you walk
the wrong passes at some m moment the
intelligence of these agents degrades
like I want to swear and throw them out
of the window. [laughter] And the
solution there are some solutions. So
one solution is editing the context. So
some of you might already know but when
working in the shell you can double
escape and then you can edit the like
the history and if you prompt for the
next solution and the next answer and
you you think oh that's not how I meant
it just escape escape edit it and you
can just go go up the chain of prompts
and you can edit back the whole context
and that's how you at the moment do
context engineering by yourself. The
other thing is so these models have this
compact mode compression of the context.
So when the context is full it has
autoco compression for example but it's
intransparent. So we don't know what the
model is doing how the coding agent is
doing and how it summarized the context.
[clears throat]
So what we need to do is uh um or what
we tend to do is ask it to summarize by
ourself then check the the summarization
and hand it over to the next agent. So
this is works quite well. Um
coming to the uh second half of our talk
experiments with multi- aent
orchestration and the uh paradigm of
mixture of coding agents. uh we uh gave
them the skill to manage other coding
agents via T-Mo shell. So it's an agent
MD and we tell the codeex agent use this
to spin spawn another coding agents
spawn some clothes spawn some codecs and
using this you can spawn a lot of
codings as much as you want.
Uh the experiment we do is ask them to
build an agent and so we have the coding
agents really really important building
blocks on our way to AGI and then the
others are search and deep research
agents as yeah everybody from of us
could come up with a good idea but look
to the outside the ideas are all there
people are inventing a lot of stuff and
it's impossible to to gather all the
ideas and reflect and evaluate. So let's
do let's have the agents do the work for
us.
First experiment
codeex versus code like it comes out of
the installation only one prompt one
shot please build a a search agent is in
the stren agent framework which is a
nice framework from Amazon uh and let's
see how it plays out. So we deployed
like 20 agents and used our metrics tool
to collect the statistics and we see
okay nice experience everybody every
agent finds a solution. So this is new.
So remembering the meter chart. So when
we remember three years, two years, one
year ago, that wasn't possible. Right
now they run for about 20 or 30 minutes
and come back with a search agent able
to search via pray, via Google, via Tili
for information in the internet just
with a single simple prompt. uh and in
our race uh codeex had a little edge uh
uh for co for clothes but this is maybe
because we are more used right now to to
work with codeex and the prompt was
primed a little bit um so that's how a
typical solution looks like many of you
might have seen similar uh approaches it
iterates through the tasks it's planning
the task of searching and then
summarizing and delivering the answer
and if you uh uh prompt it right, it can
deliver a structured answer which you
can use to score and compare the model.
Um the question is [clears throat]
do uh agents rule help when tasking the
agents to build agents? And it turns out
uh they'll do
um [clears throat]
and what we done what we've done here is
uh just a simple um agents MD file with
rules uh like where to find
configuration uh where to find the key.
So that's something we observed like the
agents not knowing where it's looking
everywhere and it's spending tokens for
nothing. Yeah. And also you might want
to have some patterns you observed from
yourself which are nice and that's how
you specify and you see okay specifying
some rules helps in improving the model
score. But what you also see and that
was a little bit surprising is it
increases token use. So one might have
thought uh guiding the model to better
solutions will help in in saving uh uh
costs and runtime and tokens and tool
use but it actually increased it and
that's because it knows the
possibilities of the framework and the
tools there and was able to come up with
much much better solutions.
[cough]
Um, next thing in the orchestration
pattern thing is a pattern we use by
ourself. And here we we uh spun up the
experiment is having an arena mode and
in corporation mode. So running an
experiment with 20 agents in parallel
already is like a kind of arena because
you can pick up the best solutions from
the 20. But having the the agents decide
by themsel is also enhancing. And you
can have a second iteration where you
give the one agent the results of the
other and the other the results of the
one. And you can ask them please reflect
about the solution. What's better than
yours? What you what could be helpful in
improvement? And you can uh give them
the chance to improve and refine and
reflect their own solution. And it turns
out it's really helpful. Yeah. Not only
because of the refinement of the chance
to spend more test time to improve the
solution, but also when having different
agents. For example, the the set model
behaves different than the codeex model
and the information and the ideas they
come up is are different and models who
get the chance to see other good
solutions are able to reflect and
integrate this in their approach. And
you see that the score is increasing and
the refinement u um budget is is much
much lower than u the building up u uh
budget because it just needs to adapt
some of the components and don't need to
build up the whole uh um system.
Um that was a funny observation. One of
the agent though the prompt was pr
primed with the arena example and how
you can look up the solution of the
other and use it to improve your your
your own solution and one came up with
arena solution for the search agent in
itself. So this was like another uh
self-reflecting pattern and it helped
really really in the uh um in the end in
the results. Yeah. Last part of the talk
is how we used the uh um our GitHub tool
and skill. So so far we've seen the the
metrics and the analytics skill for
coding agents. We've seen the the
orchestration skill how to orchestrate
the others. And then is the question how
to come up with good solutions. And it
might be interesting for the agent not
to only search uh uh via internet search
but also to look at good solutions from
GitHub. And the first thing with the
hammer in the hand everything looks like
a nail being data guys and crawler and
the scraper guys. We crawled and scraped
the GitHub API and we extracted agents
MD clo MDs readme and so on and we made
some statistic and we see like the
trends and you see like the moment when
clo picked up and then like four or six
weeks ago when the other agents agents
MD was uh uh published in my I think and
that's where you see like an increase
and it's an unfair advantage because
every other agent is using agents MD and
cloud MD is only used by cl uh skills
are exploding right now. So we we uh uh
here you see the skills per project but
you see like in average five or six
skills per project though the number is
much much higher than you see here.
[clears throat]
Then uh we use the the intelligence of
the the models to classify these files.
So uh uh rules dab or uh kind of rules
kind of project uh uh product life cycle
system life cycle genai focus agentic
level and so on and then we we try to
extract patterns we observe and to find
good solutions
[clears throat]
um having a vector database at our
hands. So we've put on all the the agent
MD in it and we ask our uh agent uh to
uh uh retrieve and rerank good solutions
depending on the question and we
employed some metadata filters. So it
was is able to to filter recent projects
and filter uh u specific agents MD or
like u um reflecting on uh the kind of
the ripple and so on. And uh it
interestingly with the question create
an agent MD. So it has the pos ability
to reflect on some uh of the results. it
came up with really really good
solutions and it improved the um results
as well and if you've been into meta
prompting you'll see that the prompt
these agents come up they are better
than the prompts we come up and if they
have the chance to to look at other good
solutions it it it improves the quality
even more.
Yeah. And that's it finally. So the best
agent found every information about me.
Yeah, luckily. So there isn't too much
about me on the internet. It's a hard
task I can tell you. Uh but it managed
and um yeah, so if you are interested in
getting to know more about this or in
the scripts and the agency, just contact
me. Let's get in touch. Let's talk and
chat about it and then I can send you
some of this and even give you access to
our Q&A assistant. Thank you.
>> Wow.
Heat. [music]
Heat.
[music]